<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Mad Ramblings of a Lunatic Hacker]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-01T11:56:52-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven! Ragnarök]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sightread Your Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/11/29/sightread-your-code/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T09:50:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/11/29/sightread-your-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Sightreading is an essential skill for any musician. Turns out it's pretty
important for good software developers as well.</em></p>

<h2>What is Sightreading?</h2>

<p>I've been listening to a ton of <a href="http://rubyrogues.com">Ruby Rogues</a>, so let's begin with a
definition.</p>

<p>From Wikipedia,</p>

<blockquote><p> <strong>Sightreading</strong> <em>is the reading and performing of a piece of written music,
specifically when the performer has not seen it before.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Musicians are always evaluated on their ability to read and interpret musical
scores on command, a musician's time isn't cheap and rehearsing a specific piece
of music is a privilege reserved often reserved for school ensembles and AAA
film score recordings. I exaggerate a little, but honestly, professional
musicians are not afforded a lot of rehearsal time. They are instead expected to
walk up to a piece, play their bit expressively while fitting in with the rest
of the ensemble perfectly, sometimes without ever hearing them.</p>

<p>If you're wondering how on Earth this could possibly relate to software, look no
further than your first day on your current project. Most software developers
don't have the privilege of starting from scratch when they begin a new job or
contract.  Instead we are thrown into an existing one and expected to decrease
the bug count. Some people might say that's an unfair expectation, but it is, in
fact, no different from expecting a professional musician to walk into the
studio, read your score, play their piece once or twice, then collect their
check and leave.</p>

<p>Western music has a complex but accepted system of notation that all musicians
and composers are expected to be familiar with. On top of this base language
there are sets of idioms particular to certain genres. By writing works in this
language and leveraging (often subconsciously) these idioms composers create
music that musicians can read and follow and interpret even <em>as</em> they play.</p>

<p>In the case of software development, the language and idioms are still present,
but they are the languages and idioms of computer programs rather than those of
western music.</p>

<h2>Sightreading Code</h2>

<p>So what's the point of sightreading code? Here's three scenarios from every
stage of one's career.</p>

<ol>
<li>You're fresh out of University and in a technical interview. You've been
  asked to find and fix the two known bugs in a text formatting program.</li>
<li>You've just started your first day at a new job and you've been tasked with
  extending an existing project with new features.</li>
<li>You're a super celebrity master contractor and people pay you way too much
  money. You walk up to code you've never seen before and need to make magic
  happen in order to justify your absurd cost.</li>
</ol>


<p>In each case your value hinges on picking up a brand new codebase and running
with it. Since you can't control the quality of code you didn't write you can't
make any excuses regarding what's already written. At this point you have two
options. Skim the code, or read it all.</p>

<p>I will tell you right now, <strong>skimming doesn't work.</strong> You can't read every other
line or seek for specific variable names and actually follow what is going on.
When you do so, you screw it up.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Slight boorishness follows</em></p>

<blockquote><p>If you ask me a question about my code, I'm going to assume you've read every
relevant line.</p></blockquote>

<p>Relevant lines are tough to pin down, but at the very least the entire method in
question is a good start. When you haven't done so, it's plain disrespectful and
arrogant on your part, especially when your question is answered (or nullified)
by something directly in that body of code. By skimming and then bringing up
something you saw during the skim, you waste your time and mine.</p>

<p>Everyone who has taught me up until a year ago will roll their eyes at me for
this because I was the best at skimming (meaning I was the worst reader/pupil) I
actively avoid jumping to conclusions about what I read and take a concerted
effort to answer as much as I can on my own before escalating a problem.
Furthermore, when I do I often have a much better handle on what question I am
asking than I would otherwise have had.</p>

<p>In all seriousness, when you do this I start to think about spending less time
with you. I warn everyone I'm comfortable warning not to skim <strong><em>ever</em></strong>.
Including you, dear reader.</p>

<p>Since skimming code doesn't work, our only remaining option is to actually read
the code completely. This probably sounds like a lot of work, that's because it
is, but so is reading and performing an entire ten minute piece in half an hour
and musicians still manage to get it done.</p>

<p>In order to determine how we can become more effective code sightreaders, we
again look to our musician friends who have been doing this for some time.
Musicians who want to improve their sightreading do the following things.</p>

<h3>Musicians Know and Practice Scales</h3>

<p>Musicians who practice their scales are the ones with the best technical chops,
their fingers are the most agile, their articulation superb and they're
comfortable with any given set of notes.</p>

<p>For programmers who wish to improve sightreading, there's simple no replacement
for knowing the language you're in. If you've never looked at C before, you'll
spend 20 minutes figuring out what <code>int main() {</code> is, or spend that time
figuring out the precise semantics of a line ending conditional in Ruby.</p>

<p><em>If you don't know the language, you'll spend time figuring out what the
language is doing instead of what the program is doing. Know your language.</em></p>

<h3>Musicians Study Music Theory</h3>

<p>Every musician who works with written music needs at least a basic understanding
of music theory. Without it, reading music, let alone interpretting it, is
impossible. Over time many musicians gain an intuitive understanding of theory.
They realize all major scales are the same but starting from a different note,
then slowly absorb more as they go. But some of the best musicians actively
learn theory as theory and can leverage that to do amazing things as Jazz
improvisers, composers, and virtuosos.</p>

<p>As computer scientists, we need to know the design patterns used in our field.
Decorators, strategies, delegation, they all need to be second nature if we
intend to approach a new body of code and immediately see what's going on.
Additionally, these patterns establish a common vocabulary you can use to
discuss code with other programmers regardless of their language and experience.
If you both know the patterns, they can add precision and expressiveness to your
non-executable communication.</p>

<p><em>Knowing patterns allows you to see and apply them instantly when you enter a
new codebase or team. Use them as a common vocabulary.</em></p>

<h3>Musicians Sightread During Practice</h3>

<p>Lastly, and hopefully most obviously, musicians practice the act of sightreading
during their own self-directed practice. My high school band director, once said
to our ensemble that if you do something for the first time during the show,
you're practicing in front of a live audience, not performing.</p>

<p>Likewise, don't assume that if you know your languange and some patterns you'll
be an extraordinary sightreader. You need to apply that knowledge frequently if
you want to temper it into skill. Trust me, you do <em>not</em> want to do it on the
job your first few times. If you do, you'll likely feel rushed and sink back
into skimming. So find an open source library you use, pop into it's source code
and get reading.</p>

<p><em>Don't do your practicing in front of a live audience. Read open source code in
order to get better at sightreading.</em></p>

<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>

<p>Thus far I've made the assumption that you will have no control over the
codebases that you sightread. While this is often the case when starting out,
we often spend a significant amount of time with one codebase and start to grow
into and learn it. While this certainly helps, one of the main differences
between musical scores and software projects is that individual scores seldom
change between performances whereas software is in constant flux. If you wrote
it a week ago you'll be sightreading it again next week. If you wrote it a month
ago, how many hands have been at it since you last looked at it? Sightreading is
a constant and ongoing process in software.</p>

<p>As a writer of software, you can and should take steps to make your software
more sightreadable but I've throw a big wall of text at everyone so I think
I'll tackle that subject at a later date.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[There Are 10 Types of Tests. You Need Both of Them]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/10/28/there-are-10-types-of-tests-you-need-both-of-them/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-28T02:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/10/28/there-are-10-types-of-tests-you-need-both-of-them</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of the last year, and especially in the last two to three months
I have been internalizing and witnessing for myself the extreme benefits of
accompanying your code with a test suite which matches your code in quality.
By this I mean that it is difficult (and damn frustrating) to write good tests
for poor code. At my current skill level as a programmer there's code in my
primary code base that is so bad (yep, I wrote that code too) that I am unable
to write good tests for it. Up until four or five weeks ago, coinciding with my
second readings of <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/achbd/the-rspec-book">The RSpec Book</a>, and <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/hwcuc/the-cucumber-book">The Cucumber Book</a>, sitting in
as a guest panelist on <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/book-club-exceptional-ruby/">Ruby Rogues</a>, and watching a bunch of
<a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/screencasts">Destroy All Software</a>, I realized that in order to gain the benefits of TDD
being touted by some of the most respected members of the Ruby community, I
needed better tests. Specifically better isolated tests.</p>

<h2>Isolated Tests</h2>

<p>I recently had to completely justify my desire to add and grow isolated tests
for production code. The argument against doing so was simply that if the <em>whole
point</em> of isolated tests is to know when something breaks in the future, an
integrated test suite will pick up those failures just as well. Therefore
isolated tests are a waste of time and engineering effort.</p>

<p>This argument <em>is</em> correct, provided the only thing you use your isolated tests
for is protection from regressions. However, doing so leaves out what is to my
mind the <strong>greatest</strong> and most profound advantage of isolated testing, which is
immediate, focused feedback. I definitely think I'm inventing terms here so
please indulge me while I clarify them.</p>

<ul>
<li>Immediate: <em>The result (success or failure) can be observed right away.</em></li>
<li>Focused: <em>The cause of any failure is known to be within the system under
test.</em></li>
</ul>


<p>Anyone who has worked in software for a substantial amount of time knows that
we are each our own worst enemy and the temptation to add unnecessary complexity
is a constant bother. How many of us have added arguments to methods only to
use the default value every time. I call these bullshit arguments, because they
piss me off when I have to put up with them. The joy in a test with truly
immediate feedback is the laser focus that they give you when working on a
system. You're literally doing one thing at a time and checking that you get the
expected result even when it isn't success. When you get the failure you expect,
you simply move on, and when you get an unexpected failure it causes you to
identify the disparity between your mental model of the system and the computer
model and correct it. Since these tests are isolated and generally run in less
than a second, there is essentially no penalty for running the tests with
monstrous frequency. When you do have to stop, it is to make a correction,
even if it is just a mental correction. The time you save fixing it early is
more than enough to justify the low cost of running the test.</p>

<p>One of the downsides of this type of testing is that you are treating anything
which isn't the system under test as an external service and therefore
stubbing the interactions with it. This works great for fast, clean-room tests
but it means that the burden of ensuring that the assumptions you make in one
test are validated in the respective tests for your other systems is entirely on
the programmer and since programmers are human, this will eventually lead to
mistakes.</p>

<p>My personal favorite aspect of isolated tests is how informative they can be
about your system. It's pretty common knowledge that if your tests are a pain in
the ass to write, it's a good indication that your code is too-tightly coupled
and refactoring to follow the <a href="http://avdi.org/devblog/2011/07/05/demeter-its-not-just-a-good-idea-its-the-law/">Law of Demeter</a> and <a href="http://blog.rubybestpractices.com/posts/gregory/055-issue-23-solid-design.html">SOLID</a> design
principles is a good idea.</p>

<h2>Integrated Tests</h2>

<p>One of the scariest things that happened to me in recent memory was discovering
that people were surprised when after arguing in favor of getting higher quality
unit tests I was still unsatisfied because our integrated tests also needed
attention and improvement. I found this a little disturbing (okay, I found this
really disturbing) because I can't imagine how long it would take to manually
verify that I didn't overlook anything in the major refactoring or feature
addition I just performed. I certainly don't budget the time to manually test
every resource and parameter combination by hand. I might do so initially
because a major disadvantage to integrated tests is in the difficulty of doing
exploratory testing at this level. As a result, when writing integrated tests, I
tend to rely on manual experimentation to determine how my system behaves in
undefined situations, make a decision on the appropriateness of that behavior
and then solidify that set of interactions into a group of tests. One of the
nice things about integrated tests is that once written, they tend not to change
unless your expected end-user behavior changes. This is afforded by the
"bigger picture" nature of integrated tests where you are less concerned with
the exact behavior of any one unit and instead are validating the result of
system-wide operation and interaction. Thus, integrated tests are largely immune
to internal refactoring.</p>

<p>As one can imagine, the strengths of isolated tests are the weaknesses of
integrated tests. When something is wrong, particularly in a complex interaction
that touches many parts of the system, it can be unclear exactly where the
problem in the codebase is when an integrated test fails. If you get an actual
exception, you'll have a stacktrace to guide you, but those tend to be unhelpful
errors like an unexpected nil and rarely is it obvious at what level the nil was
assigned and how long it had been propagated upward until the failure. So it
can be said that integrated tests are not focused since there is no indication
of precisely where in the system the failure has occurred. Additionally,
integrated tests mandate that you test your full software stack. Any persistence
layers, external services, background tasks, and other specific tools you're
using should be tested during this phase. As you can imagine testing all of
these things takes time and computing power. It is not feasible to expect even
a subset of an integrated test suite to run in the same magnitude of time as
isolated tests, what this means is the tests are no longer immediate. Thus,
they are not suitable for running at every pass of your TDD cycle. Only when you
believe the feature to be complete.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>So if isolated tests don't identify incongruities between subsystems and
integrated tests are too slow to run during an immediate feedback TDD cycle,
which do you use? As you may have surmised from the title, the answer is...
both.</p>

<p><a href="http://pragprog.com/book/hwcuc/the-cucumber-book">The Cucumber Book</a> suggests that "It's sometimes said that unit tests ensure
you 'build the thing right', while acceptance tests ensure you 'build the
right thing'." I also like Avdi Grim's simile of mocks being like hydrogen
peroxide in that they both fizz up around problems.</p>

<p>With our twin goals of systematic coverage and focus during development in mind,
let's recap how each set of tests is used.</p>

<p>When you know what you you're building but not how, reach for the integrated
tests. Define the desired outcome at the high level and then run that test again
when you think you've got it down. Start thinking about the different aspects of
that problem and decomposing them. Then devise a system of smaller tests
mirroring the smaller objects and functions you'll use to accomplish that goal.
Isolated tests are there once you're ready to do exactly that. There to aid
you in that mission and guide you toward good design decisions. "I'll do what
the tests tell me" is not an uncommon phrase from me.</p>

<p><em>Isolated regression tests are a side effect of good TDD, they're more important
during the process than after.</em></p>

<p><em>Integrated tests are the ones you bring home and show your mother. The ones you
can be proud of at the end of the day.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CoffeeScript: An Outsider Opinion]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/07/03/coffeescript-an-outsider-opinion/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-03T18:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/07/03/coffeescript-an-outsider-opinion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on CoffeeScript from a server-side developer just getting started with
frontend and JavaScript development.</em></p>

<p>Firstly, if you’re unfamiliar with CoffeeScript, I recommend reading elsewhere
for a proper overview and introduction. The CoffeeScript homepage and the
Introductory Chapter of The Litte CoffeeScript Book are good resources for that.
If you’re really impatient CoffeeScript is in the author’s own words
"JavaScript’s less ostentatious kid brother." I’ve also heard it called
"Javascript for Ruby and Python programmers" and "What Javascript should have
been" by several of my peers. It also seems that it could’ve been called
CilantroScript<a href="http://coffeescript.com">1</a> as it seems to have an instantly polarizing effect on people
in online communities such as Reddit and the Ruby on Rails community.</p>

<h2>So why did I start working with CoffeeScript? A number of reasons.</h2>

<p>I am a backend developer and want to grow my frontend skills.
1. I’m starting to experiment with Node.js on the server.
2. Jeremy Ashkenas’s talk at CodeConf on literate programming blew my mind.
3.I know Ruby, so I should enjoy a “Javascript for Rubyists”, right?
4. It is going to be a Ruby on Rails default soon so I might as well check it
out now.
5. I like new and shiny things.</p>

<p>One of the quandries I faced when deciding to learn CoffeeScript was the fact
that I don’t know JavaScript. I spent 6 months noodling with Ruby before picking
up Rails and am still getting my feet wet with Python before taking Django for a
spin. So why on Earth would someone with my MO pick up CoffeeScript without
first becoming proficient with javascript? (Aside: I’m tired of the CamelCasing)
The answer comes from the first sentence (topic sentence, for those still in Jr.
High School) in the second paragraph of the coffeescript home page.</p>

<blockquote><p>The golden rule of CoffeeScript is: “It’s just JavaScript”.</p></blockquote>

<p>As it turns out that isn’t entirely true since coffeescript is a class based
object oriented language and javascript is prototype based. This was actually a
mark against coffeescript for me since part of my desire to learn javascript was
to dally in prototype based OOP. (Luckily there’s still Io for that.) But for
the most part Coffee really is just javascript.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT: Jeremy Ashkenas has kindly clarified this point for me.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>CoffeeScript is prototype based to the precise same extent that JavaScript is.
The "class" keyword is just sugar for JavaScript’s constructor function +
prototype chain combination. To mangle Shakespeare:</p>

<blockquote><p>What’s in a name? That which we call a class by any other name would smell
as sweet. Call it a prototype if you like — it’s the same thing in code.</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Thanks Jeremy, apologies for misapprehending.</p>

<h2>So why the bother?</h2>

<p>A while back I invested some of my hard-earned and short-in-supply cash to pick
up a ten-pack of PeepCode tokens. I have to say, I’ve derived an intense amount
of value from PeepCode but more on that later. I started with PeepCode’s Meet
CoffeeScript, had they produced a Meet JavaScript I would have started there,
but they didn’t. It took around six hours to watch the three and a half hour
video. Almost immediately after, I started PeepCode’s Meet Node.js screencast
and attempted to do it in javascript for about eight minutes. The appeal of
coffeescript was immediately clear.</p>

<p>In JavaScript, I have to worry about whether or not every line ends in a
semicolon, that there are no extraneous commas, yet commas where necessary,
and that I’ve remembered the var keyword on all my local variables. All that
stuff is important in JavaScript it doesn’t actually effect my application in
any way. In CoffeeScript, I can focus on the behavior of my code rather than the
presentation of it. Instead of scrutinizing each line for a semicolon and each
block for matching curly braces. I’m affirming that all my variables are scoped
properly and that my code does what I want it to do. It doesn’t add much to
javascript but rather, reduces the amount of worry and focus on what is at the
end of the day arbitrary stuff.</p>

<p>Sure, I have Vim configured with the fantastic Synastic plugin and I get
notified when I drop a semicolon or have an unmatched brace but what’s the
point? Basic sanity checking is all it can really do. Why even waste the time
to go back and insert those in the first place?</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I’m still continuing my education in JavaScript, CoffeeScript, jQuery, Node.js,
and prototype-based OOP. I’m armed with the beta copy of the CoffeeScript book
by Trevor Burnham from Pragmatic Programmers. I fully intend to use CoffeeScript
for all of my development in Javascript environments, server- and client-side,
work and play, for the foreseeable future.</p>

<h2>My CoffeeScript Resources</h2>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://coffeescript.com">The CoffeeScript Website and Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://peepcode.com/products/coffeescript">Meet CoffeeScript</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pragprog.com/book/tbcoffee/coffeescript">CoffeeScript: Accelerated JavaScript Development by Trevor Burnham</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jashkenas.github.com/coffee-script/documentation/docs/command.html">The Annotated CoffeeScript Source</a></li>
<li><a href="http://arcturo.com/library/coffeescript/index.html">The Little CoffeeScript Book</a></li>
<li><a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596517748/">Javascript: The Good Parts by Douglas Crockford</a></li>
<li><a href="http://eloquentjavascript.net/">Eloquent Javascript by Marjin Haverbeke</a></li>
<li><a href="http://autotelicum.github.com/Smooth-CoffeeScript/">Smooth CoffeeScript by autotelicum</a> via
<a href="http://twitter.com/raynos2">@Raynos2</a></li>
</ol>


<hr />

<ol>
<li>Cilantro (or Coriander) is an herb which to some people tastes pleasantly
citrus-like and to others is rank and revolting or soapy. As a result many
people either love it or hate it. Few are ambivalent about Cilantro. The same
is true of CoffeeScript in my observation.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
