<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bio | Mad Ramblings of a Lunatic Hacker]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/categories/bio/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-15T13:03:35-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven! Ragnarök]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who I Am and Where I Am Going]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/11/28/who-i-am-and-where-i-am-going/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-28T13:35:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.nuclearsandwich.com/blog/2011/11/28/who-i-am-and-where-i-am-going</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>So <em>who am I now?</em></h2>

<p>Basically I am not anybody. I'm a student of Computer Science
and Mathematics at San José State University. I have been fiddling with
computers my whole life but would say that the decision to embrace quality
software design only happened about a year and a half ago. My entire formal
education save for one functional programming class which I only had last semester
has been Java but for a token course each in C, C++, and Assembly taught by a
professor who had to mentally translate everything into Java and then translate
it back to answer questions. As a result, I'm really behind in a lot of stuff I
shouldn't be behind in.</p>

<p>In the past two years I've found myself making money doing things in Ruby.
The best thing about Ruby is that it's fun to do things right, compared to Java
where you are actively punished for trying to do so. I have made it my business
to be a good Rubyist and live up to <a href="/blog/2011/08/19/why-ruby-needs-heroes">those who inspired me</a> to learn the
language and participate in the community. As part of this process I've read
voraciously on Ruby and software craftmanship, lurked in IRC, and made a
nuisance of myself at conferences and Ruby meetups. The process has made me a
lot of new friends, at times both inflated and deflated my ego, and overall
given me a much grander perspective on what the important things are in life and
in software development.</p>

<p>Because it's rather difficult to code in 90 minute spats with shoddy internet,
the great majority (read: all but school related) of my projects are in-progress
and incomplete. I <em>despise</em> this about myself. One of the main things I still
suck at is cranking out a project in a weekend. And since most of my projects
are started to apply a specific bit of knowledge or insight, or leverage a
specific language or language feature I wish to do more with, I tend to start
a new one more often than continue work on the old ones. While I don't think it
too much of a problem, it'd definitely feel better to have one or two completed
works in my portfolio that <em>aren't</em> a top-down recursive descent parser, of
which I have three with a fourth (Clojure, this time) in progress.</p>

<h2>Just <em>where is he going with this..?</em></h2>

<p>Well now, I'm working as a Ruby developer, I've finally made it to a Railsbridge
workshop and absolutely love teaching there. More to the credit of Steve's open
commit policy than to my own artistry I am a contributor to <a href="http://hackety-hack.com">Hackety-Hack.com</a></p>

<p>I've just decided to apply to January's Ruby Mendicant University session though
the upcoming weeks are going to be maddeningly busy for me and I may have to
hold off until the next one comes around. I had the pleasure of taking Peter
Cooper's Ruby Reloaded course which I highly recommend for those who learned
just enough Ruby to be potent with Rails but still aren't sure what's going on
in some cases.</p>

<p>I've picked up Clojure and and revisited Haskell and am loving both. I've got a
few ideas in mind for beginning Clojure projects and am preparing for a return
to Archlinux as my primary OS as I simply can't tolerate OS X any longer.</p>

<p>I want to start being the type of programmer that inspired me to get as far as
I've had the privilege of getting thus far and I'll do it one application,
library, and blog article at a time. Starting...</p>

<p><strong><em>now.</em></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
